this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for software engineering radio today
with me on the show is dr. Michaela
Greiner Michaela is a software engineer
and a tech entrepreneur
she helped companies to get the most out
of code reviews by offering code review
workshops and my optimizing code review
process prior she was a software
engineer and researcher at Microsoft
where she worked with teams such as
office windows and visual studio to
improve the software engineering
lifecycle she has a PhD from Delft
University of Technology and 15 years of
experience analyzing and improving
software engineering processes she also
runs the software engineering unlocked
podcast welcome to the show Mikaella
hello - I'm really happy to be here the
topic of today's show is code reviews
which are your absolute expertise but
what exactly is a code review could you
share your definition of what a code
review is I would say in a traditional
sense
a code review is a feedback process or a
feedback loop so you can say one person
developed some code might be a bug fix
or it's a part of a feature and then at
least one other colleague or peer looks
over the code changes and gives feedback
but all the time that I spend
understanding code reviews I like to see
it or view it as a collaboration
mechanism so it's really that we stay in
contact and discuss code and bond
together yeah
so those are already two goals that you
stay in it firstly giving feedback and
secondly a means of communication about
code so is that summary correct yes yes
that's very true that's very true yeah
and why do we do code reviews what do
they add because there are other means
of giving feedback like unit tests or
integration tests what do code review
specifically add to the process of
giving feedback as a means of
communication about the source code
but I think code reviews they have their
own role and goals right so for example
with the testing you're actually looking
at the correctness of the code or if the
code is bug free order the cases that
you're covered you know perform as you
expected
I think Cody we are completely different
in that regard because what you do dare
you get feedback from your peers about
for example the readability of the code
but also the maintainability you also
got a knowledge sharing aspect so
because your colleagues will look over
what you actually developed they know
what you're working on didn't know how
the system looks like and I think that's
really a really important aspect of code
reviews and you don't get that with with
testing for example to summarize that
it's like testing but code reviews are
richer there's more that you can get out
of a code review than simply
understanding if the code is working
correctly I think they are actually not
even a good mechanism for ensuring that
the code behaves correctly I know that
people stayed one of the primary goals
that they find defects and you know have
accident prevention from code reviews
but corabeth's aren't really designed
for that people are much better to
detect other things right so if that's
your primary goal then I would say you
should invest more in testing for
example or monitoring or things like
that but people are good in
understanding things that the system
can't do so for example they would say
that design pattern doesn't fit right
there or isn't implemented in there in
the correct way or that piece of code is
somehow fragile or not maintainable I
don't understand how you wrote that so
you're improving the code base and the
quality of the code base but it's not
really about the back prevention there
is an aspect of it so we did some
studies at Microsoft and others studied
that as well and we saw that around 15%
of the review comments are about defects
that's only a small portion most of it
more than 50% is really about
maintainability of the code readability
of the code that's maybe why I even why
my definition of code reviews is more as
a collaboration mechanism to just
highlight to people that the benefits
that they get out are much richer I mean
obviously you don't want to pass on
those 15% of effects but the time that
you're spend is it's really about
knowledge sharing it's about
collaboration and talking about the
coded I think code reviews are so good
because they have the reality right
there so it's somehow grounded in code
you know your discussion isn't about
some high level feature and you're just
imagining how that would be and the
other tries to explain how they have
implemented or will implement but you
see it right there it's written there
and that's how it is and so I think it's
a very grounded discussion basis that
actually segues really nice into my next
question because you just mentioned that
just 15% about comments on code reviews
are about defects or bugs and that 50%
is about maintainability so I was going
to ask what evidence do we have that
code reviews work what we know about the
effects of code reviews so again I would
say it really depends on what work means
to you so if you talk about whether code
reviews improve the code base then I
would say yes there is evidence for
example they have been studies at
Microsoft and at Google that look at
whether code reviews trigger changes and
yes at Google for example 80% of all the
code reviews trigger a change now of
course you might say well how do we know
that those changes you know are
improvements but I would argue that most
likely if two people or two engineers
agree on a change and they say it makes
sense then it will be an improvement to
the code at Microsoft event even a
little bit further and we work with
several teams to understand what
constitutes valuable feedback code
review feedback and developers clearly
indicated that feedback that leads to
change is valuable to them so yeah I
would say my answer is yes there is
evidence that there are positive change
is happening to the code base but I also
think that maybe we don't even need that
scientific evidence
come to that conclusion just if we think
about our self better is that via
writing code or maybe we are just
writing something right if we ask
somebody else with a different pair of
eyes write with a different perspective
to look through that with the different
expertise maybe what we have will be
improved
that's why high quality publications for
example have editors of proof writers so
I think that we know that it will work
in that respect but now if you think
does it work in other areas for example
for knowledge sharing then I would say
yes obviously because if you actually
look at the review so if it's not just a
window dressing activity that you do and
nobody actually looks at the review then
you will know more about what's going on
in your system and if somebody points
something else you will learn so yes you
have those aspects and I think they work
maybe a more tricky question is whether
or not they are worth while the
additional work that you put in right
because they are expensive I mean they
require quite some work from the
engineers
and I definitely want to get into this
trade-off between spending time on a
code review and maybe spending time
elsewhere but firstly let's back up a
little bit and let's talk about the code
review process so how do we do a code
review are we in one room do we do it
remotely maybe true github what is the
setup what are different variants or
different forms you can do a code review
could you take us through your favorite
form of doing code reviews
yeah that sounds good so the actual life
cycle of code review or the process can
look quite different so I start with a
very informal type that's we call it the
over-the-shoulder review which just
means that at one point a colleague
comes to you or you ask them to come to
you and you just look at some piece of
code together so and they give you a
feedback about it are you discussing a
problem together so you that's one one
way to do code reviews right and you see
some similarities to pair programming
there but there's also does code reviews
and I think that's really previously how
they have been in a much more formal way
so that's on the complete different
other side right so that would be for
example code inspections it'd have been
very popular and they are much a more
formal process so you have really larger
parts of the code base that you look
through and it's a meeting line setting
there are many people and they have
checklists and inspection lists and they
go through it one by one it takes a lot
of time and they are still done it for
certain kind of software's or for
certain kind of companies you still see
inspections happening but nowadays I
think if we talk about code reviews what
we envision what's the typical process
is this asynchronous way of looking at
code so one person develops some code
let's say they have a back fix or a
feature and then they work on the code
until they are thinking they are in a
new in a good state that they solve the
problem for example and then they will
send that code depending on the tool
that you use it will look different but
somehow send that code over to
colleagues 1 2 3 colleagues and those
colleagues look at their own times
through the code and just annotated give
feedback so one of the areas where code
reviews have been really popular was the
open source community and there they
used email for example to do that so
somebody would to create a patch for
some open ticket and then they would
create a patch so package of code and
send that via email and people would
start to discuss that patch on the email
list so you would say oh you know you
haven't seen you haven't looked at that
corner case or I'm not so happy with
Doubleday
that you did there or the design doesn't
fit or something like that right so you
would comment about that and the really
nice thing was especially in the
open-source community that because it
happened on this email list people
stayed in forms even if you are not
commenting on you could always read it
so there's some traceability aspect
nowadays I think a lot of teams do it
either with the standalone tool so for
example Garriott or crucible or
fabricator so these are all code review
tools and you can imagine that it's like
an IDE so your integrated development
environment but you have some special
functionality to comment on that and
then you sent it feedback and people
will change the code based on what what
you said and so it's an iterative
process as well so I think that's a very
very common scenario right now also pull
requests so with the with the area of
pull requests code reviews become more
popular because you just have to imagine
that instead of you pushing the code
somewhere it's always the same person
that is in control somehow somebody had
to pull your version in and very natural
step that they would do is they look
over what they are actually pulling in
right so they look over the changes that
happened and maybe give some feedback at
least they say it's ok oh it's not ok
I'm going to merge it or I'm not coming
to merge and I think in this pull
request model more and more companies
also naturally fall into that code
review habit right so they are doing
code reviews whenever they have to do a
pull request or for other systems now a
merge request and things like that
what you're saying I think is that
there's a large variety of ways to do a
coach review and that is a matter of
practice what fits your company your
code base more yeah but do you think
that for some types of code bases some
types of reviews fit more I think you
hints this a little bit when you said
for some types of software a meeting
might be more needed do you think there
must be a fit between the type of review
or the form of the review and what your
company is building or how your company
is building things yes yes I think so I
mean I think it's the same as with
testing right if you have like a system
that people lives depend on you will
have a much more rigorous and probably
also much more formal process around
ensuring that everything is ok then if
you have like a website that you know
even if something slips through is a
problematic and I think nowadays people
tend to have more lightweight process in
general and I think that they still
cover a lot of the things especially for
this readability and maintainability
aspects they are they're very well
suited I think that you can have
combinations as well like you have some
you know inspections or some reviews I
mean I think for example architectural
discussions can also be seen sometimes
as code reviews right if you really look
at the code and you're deciding which
eye texture you should implement for
example I think it's as part of a code
review as well so definitely much more
broader than just reading source code
yes yes and I think it's not only about
the company but also there the current
goal that you have right what do you
want to achieve and then you will pick
one of those things so you will have an
ad hoc meeting and a more informal
process for more contagious issues right
so if you think oh you know somebody
might be offended if I say that probably
not good if you just write it and then
send the button might be better to just
call them and discuss in person you know
something like that yeah so I think it
really depends not only on the software
but also the situation that you are in
whether or not you would choose one or
the other
now I'm also thinking back at your first
remark about different goals of code
reviews like giving feedback to each
other or communicating about the code
and gaining understanding do you think
that different forms of code review also
fit different goals that you can have
with a code review I think that
different forms might prevent him to get
some of the benefits or the different
forms you know
trigger some of the drawbacks I would
rather face it a phrase it that that way
I think so for example for the pull
request it sometimes happened that you
would wait too long right so the code
review gets actually quite large you
don't see this single commits but there
are workarounds so some of the people
for example would create a pull request
at the moment that they start working on
a feature and then D they call it for
example WIP
work in progress right and so everybody
knows well that's actually not a real
pull request right now it just gives you
a window to look into what's happening
here so in general I think yeah it
depends on the goals that you have and
then how can you use the tools to
achieve your goals and if you want to
have people look at your code in smaller
increments and just be informed then you
will have workarounds if your tooling
doesn't allow that I also want to talk a
little bit about the scope of code
review what what should a code review
cover and what shouldn't a code review
cover we already talked about bugs for
example defects being in the scope of a
code review but what about a new feature
could code review be about is this
feature completed is it ready to be
released or is that something that morph
its user testing or something entirely
different
yeah again I would say it depends on
your goals I know that I say that a lot
but I think that's also why it's so so
important for the team or for the
company to have be really crystal clear
about their strategy and what do you
want I would be cautious to you know put
additional burdens on the code reviewer
without knowing why I'm doing that
say that you you shouldn't do it but
it's it's it's a definitely additional
burden right and a code reviewer isn't
your tester so they shouldn't go and
test the feature whether or not all the
features are there is for example it's
part of your definition of done and very
often for example product owners would
have those responsibilities maybe do
that as they are part of their code
review process right but I don't think
that everybody has to check for that I
think in the area of UX for example it's
gets also very interesting so if it's
easy I would do it so for example if
you're making a change to the user
interface make a screenshot and attach
it and if your tooling allows it and
there are developments in that area that
code reviews for example have runnable
versions of a current code and that are
somehow send with it so the person just
has to click and sees sees exactly what
that code entails right then yeah you
could you could think about whether or
not the person should go and check out
the the UX how it's really working but
you have to be clear if that's what you
want maybe it's just one team right
maybe it's just the UX team that has
that process because for them it makes
sense and is it is it actually connected
to your code maybe you don't have to
have the code there then why is it part
of the code review process so I think
the most important thing is that you are
very reflective about what you want to
achieve and as it fit very well into
your process into your practice are you
achieving it in an effective and
efficient way I think the biggest
takeaway for me here is that before you
start doing code reviews within a
company you should make it clear what
the goal is so is the goal to check
features and releases is the goal to
have less bugs is the code to the code
review to have a better quality of the
code and then while you're doing code
reviews you should actually reflect back
on that goal and say hey are the code
reviews actually reaching the goal that
we initially set in mind am i
summarizing that correctly yes exactly
so I think that one of the biggest
benefits that teams get out of is that
knowledge is really shared among team
members so if somebody is sake
others know what's going on and know
about the codebase so you're breaking up
those working in silos style of workings
I think if you Dan want to achieve
different things you have to be as you
said very conscious about what do you
want to achieve and how would I decide
my code review process to fit that need
and then also you know over time reflect
I'm actually achieving what I wanted to
achieve with that and if not change it
so I would zoom in a little bit onto the
two sides of code review because of
course there's a side of giving feedback
and there's the side of receiving
feedback so I really want to hear your
tips for both sides but let's start with
the giving feedback sides what are your
best practices to give feedback in a
constructive way to make sure that the
other party actually understands what
you're saying and that their feelings
aren't heard in such a way that they're
not open for more feedback as you said
there's much that can be done right so I
would say if I'm the code reviewer the
first question that I would ask myself
is how can I add value and very often in
life that's a question you can ask
yourself right how can I add value and
then the second question is how can I
convey that value in a positive and
constructive and respectful way so it's
really really important the way you give
feedback as you said how how can I make
sure that I'm not hurting feelings
because feedback even though you know
it's well-written it's well intended it
can sting and that's just human nature
so for the person that gives feedback
yeah we have to be careful how we phrase
the feedback a good rule for example is
that you can phrase your feedback as
questions not as a demand so for example
you could say hmm what about open
requests as the name for the variable
instead of saying I'll rename the
variable to open requests and in that
way you're you leave the final decision
to the author to the developer it
actually authored the code and you also
show that you're open for discussion so
somehow it becomes a collaboration
instead of you
you're a dictator you are in control
because you're the reviewer and you say
it has to be that way something else you
can do for feedback is you can phrase it
as I messages and it's really important
so for example you could say this part
it's hard for me to understand this part
of the code right so that would be a
nice way to formulate it it's hard for
me to understand this part of the code
instead of saying oh this code is hard
to understand and there is a big
difference so one is really about me and
it's really hard to argue about that
because for me it's hard to understand
and it's easy for the other person to be
open and received as message whereby if
you say this code is hard to understand
its effect and you can't argue against
it well I understand it right so I think
that's one of the there's a subtle
difference but it's a very powerful one
and you also should make the comments
really about the code and not a person
so let's imagine you say something about
the socket connection and you could say
this code does not close the socket
connection right instead of saying you
are not closing the connection right and
while there are much more rules about
respectful and constructive feedback
that people can read about and I think
they should they should be aware of how
to phrase things in the right way but
besides how you convey the message I
think it's really important also to
think about what is the message so as I
said again how can I add the value and
it Microsoft example we did a study
where we looked at while millions of
code River comments and we classified
them into valuable and not valuable
comments for the author and it turns out
that people want to hear about defects
alternative solutions missing
validations best practices but they
don't want to hear about things that are
out of scope for the code review right
so again that's why I said previously
should you do those additional steps
well if it fits and if people agree that
it's valuable to them do them otherwise
don't do them so for example code
reviews are normally not the place to
discuss existing technical debt if it
hasn't been introduced with that change
don't go around and poke in
file and say oh look over there is
something that you could fix as well or
you know don't start planning
discussions or things that are
discussions about future things that you
should work on contrabass because people
want to have the code merged right so
they have the goal after the submitter
the author of the code is get feedback
and submit that code merge that code and
I think so we have to be conscious about
that so I would also use a checklist so
that you really know what you look for
like implementation you look at design
and architecture security data privacy
things like that and then lastly I think
it's really important when you give to
feedback so I said how to give what
feedback and then when to give the
feedback because even the best feedback
isn't really a good feedback if it's a
week later or two weeks later right
before the person can work on that and
get to it
these were all really great tips thanks
a lot so to summarize try to add value
think where can i really help try to
give feedback using the iMessage like I
cannot understand that code and all the
code is understandable keep the scope
focused on the current changes do not
bring up previous technical debt or
other issues with the code and what I
also very much liked is this checklist
so would you have an example of such a
checklist that we could for example
share in their show notes yeah I have a
checklist I can link that yes these were
all tips for the person that is giving
the comments within the scope of a coach
with you what would be your tips for the
other side how do you deal with code
reviews coming your way and with
comments about Koated you have
contributed yeah yeah I have because as
you said it's a it's a two-sided thing
right so I think for the receiving end
it's really really important to be
humble and open-minded I think for both
of them it is right but the receiving
end might feel you know if might
sometimes feel that there is a power
shift between reviewer and you know
submitter which you should work on but
yeah so feedback can sting and sometimes
I think it's important for the receiving
end to just step by step back a little
bit and calm down let your let your
reactions if you think oh that feedback
actually somehow felt uncomfortable let
it come down and look at the feedback
again at a later stage you know and then
I think it's really important also for
the receiving end to show that they
actually value and consider the feedback
in a very honest way really go and look
at the feedback and have this mindset of
people you know we are in it together
they have a shared goal they want to
increase the quality of the codebase
right and so I think it's important that
you also show that your value and
consider the feedback you know you say
you don't have to take every feedback
right it's not that because the person
said it you actually have to change
something but consider it and and also
let them know what you did about it why
you didn't change something or why you
changed it that you changed it
I think what's also important on the
receiving end is not only how you go
about the feedback that you got but also
how can you ensure that you get the
valuable feedback and there are a few
things that you can do so a very very
good tip that we saw with very high
performing teams that Microsoft is give
people a heads up especially you know if
it's it might surprise them that they
get a code review right now give them a
heads up tell them you know you can
expect a code review today from me
this way they can mentally prepared
himself and also they can plan the time
that it will take them to do peer review
and the more time they have set aside
for that the more rigorously they will
do the code review and the more they
will add value to your code and then
also ask people that are familiar with
the code base for feedback don't just
you know ask anybody it's really hard
for people that aren't familiar with the
piece of code to provide valuable
feedback and another thing that is
really important for the submitter is
that you look through your code changes
before send them out so if you have a
dedicated code review tool open them up
or if you have a giving tool open that
up and see you know what's actually
included in then change and maybe even a
different perspective can help you to
see something with clear pair of eyes
right so maybe you can spot some of the
issues so don't send sloppy mistakes
over to the other side because that will
just frustrate the other person to
summarize tips for receiving a good code
review are handing good work that you
check extra before you send it out or
you seek out people that really know the
code that could give a sensible feedback
but also try to think of people that
might have a fresh perspective and be
open mind and try to remember even
though as you say feedback and staying
that you're learning together and people
giving code reviews aren't enemies but
are actually people are trying to help
you advance and help the code base
advance yes yeah I would say so
mmm-hmm I know some people use neutral
facilitators in a code free view so what
is your perspective on that does it add
value to have someone in the room or
even in the discussion maybe on github
that is related to this specific code in
this specific code review to help
facilitate discussion do you think that
adds value or it's not worth it so I
would really really hope that you don't
need that kind of person that's my first
my first reaction to that one so I think
that if code reviews are if the process
if the team dynamics are okay then I
don't think that the facilitator is
really needed and I also it's really
hard for that person to be objective
right and and to facilitate that
discussion it's also a second person or
a third person you know that's that's
spending time to do that and I think it
somehow creates a distance between the
people that actually should work
together their peers on the other hand I
think it's really really important as
well to not close our eyes for some of
the drawbacks and not even drawbacks I
would say the ugly things that can
happen with code reviews I think we have
to be very frank that code reviews there
are stories and so we have to
acknowledge those stories where code
reviews are used for power plays you
know for sabotaging people for holding
back changes but I would argue that that
isn't really something inherit that's
inherited by the code review itself it's
something that is there because of the
team the team dynamics because of
mismatches of people so I think it's
important that we have a very safe space
for our team to grow and learn and I
think the most harmful attitude is to
say our team is the city of space to
learn and grow because then it never is
right so I think there must be a
constant and continuous effort from the
team from the people towards working to
such a safe space and that's not
exclusive to contribute it's for team
collaboration and you know work
environment in general so yeah I think
that it can be helpful to go over the
code reviews from time to time and just
really see what's going on here
if you feel that there is a toxic
situation a toxic environment then yeah
how can we make sure that people feel
safe enough to talk about that maybe
there are some personality clashes maybe
the team hasn't bonded right maybe there
are like hierarchies that play out in Co
tributes all that can happen but I think
then it's not the fault of the code
reviews it's just a code reviews
mechanism that surfaced dad and maybe
that's even good right so suddenly you
see it I mean that's what we hope that
we see it that we can identify it it can
address it and yeah we can work against
that yeah so code reviews obviously are
the place where are all sorts of team
dynamics and issues with team dynamics
surface and I really like your advice of
doing a code review review in a sense
that every once in a while you look back
at a code review and you say what was
added value how was the feedback
received should we go this way is the
code review still going towards the
goals that we set for it I really like
that but even in a very safe environment
I would say it's different if I is a
more senior person give feedback to a
junior team member than the other way
around right even if in in a super safe
environment where you really like
working with each other
seniority still has there's much a
different dynamic from a senior to a
junior than the other way around do you
agree or would you say if everyone is
super happy working together that
difference shouldn't matter at all
yeah I think 100% that's exactly what I
would say that's why I said if you say
you have a safe space or place then you
don't have it because we are all humans
and you know this will happen for
juniors it's just natural that they are
intimidated by code abuse that they are
intimidated by the role that they are
put in I mean imagine it doesn't matter
if they are receiving or providing and
they just came into that team they are
new to people that you know talk to them
or give them feedback that they interact
with they are strangers they are not
familiar with the code base they are not
familiar with the company the processes
maybe they don't even know the
technologies that they have to use right
so they are in a very vulnerable
position it's not comfortable position
to be in so when you give code review
feedback I think you always have to
reflect on the the context the
circumstances to whom do I give feedback
in which situation right and then think
about how can I use that to make it a
learning and engaging experience that
also helps to build relationships and so
especially for the new hires I I would
suggest that you do well in person code
reviews right so there will be a lot of
feedback I mean it if it's normal you
will critique many of the things because
they don't know it right now so you have
to point that out and if it's delivered
in the right way I think it's very
valuable but I would do I would not just
you know it's all read and then you
throw it over you press the button and
it's delivered I would probably do
either video chat or really walk over to
the person and say do you have time we
can go through your code review and you
know have the person show that you are
actually there for them and that right
now is the time to learn and to grow and
they aren't alone so what you're saying
is I think that in-person code reviews
really make sense for new hire so they
can get a sense of how a code review is
done and what the current team dynamic
is another thing I wanted to ask you is
code reviews isn't something that's
typically taught in university at least
we don't teach in I didn't learn it when
I was in university and also I think
winning companies is no
something that people are deliberately
thoughts so how to get better at code
reviews is there something like code
review practice can you do a fake code
review to get better at this I think I
see the same things as you for the
University I have a little bit of a hard
time to talk about because it's long
time that I have been lecturing or even
going to university but when I did well
there wasn't education on code reviews
right I hear that some of the boot comes
really briefly you know mention or
introduce people to the idea of code
reviews but I think it's the same I
don't think that it's done in a very
in-depth way and similar to companies so
with companies I'm very very aware of it
that it happens very very often
engineers are asked to do code reviews
without any training without any
introduction to what is actually
expected of them and I think it has to
do with that that it's assumed that it's
self-explanatory well how hard can it be
right open some piece of code look at it
give feedback that's it right it's but
that's falsity so as we already
discussed some of the drawbacks and you
know the pitfalls there is a lot you
should be aware of and there's a lot to
learn about how to give constructive
feedback so is just to look for how the
overall design looks like and so this a
lot that can go wrong and a lot that can
go right and organizations like
Microsoft and Google and also Facebook
they really spend time to understand the
code review practices of their engineers
because engineers spend a lot of time
doing code reviews and if you just
assume you know everything is fine and
you know we don't have to improve
somewhere that's I think the wrong
attitude that's also when I for example
go to some of my clients I see that
there is their awareness that they want
to have the benefits of the code reviews
but they're getting a lot of the
drawbacks as well and you can do
something about that and it starts maybe
a bit just with just acknowledging that
there is a lot that can be learned how
to give feedback what kind of feedback
creating awareness of the pitfalls I
think internally you could create some
company internal trainings for example
or
especially the unborn ik process that
that's what we are looking that's how a
code review looks like I think it's okay
to you know maybe pair up and show them
how would you do the code reviews right
so actually practice some of the code
reviews
very often what I see is that people
just learn by being thrown in into the
deep end so they follow code reviews and
they just read and see what other people
are discussing and then they learn that
in an well in an on-the-job way right
just by observing which is okay but
there are more effective ways to do that
and if you for example have a toxic
environment you will just amplify that
with with something like that right so
if you say our engineers just learn by
it just doing and participating in the
code review process they learn exactly
the habits that are there
so yeah they can learn the good or the
bad parts for example what you could
also do is like could have brown bags so
lunch meetings for example where people
introduce new topics and they could
reflect on code reviews and how to do
code reviews and I think there's a lot
you can do
so you said pairing up myself being
explicit about this is how we do a code
review and maybe also come together and
together reflects on the process of code
reviews to get new hires to understand
how it works but also to improve the
process as a whole
yeah I think so yeah there are several
things I mean there are their technical
aspect so what should you look for and I
think it's really fair to give people a
training for that as I said for example
with this
Kota village that I created each of
those topics can then be broken down and
looked at in depth so for example at
Google they have special trainings or
reviews of reviews so that they get
special privileges and one of them is
called the readability certification
that you can do and so they are trained
for each of the language so let's say
for example for JavaScript there is one
of those programs and then there will be
one or for Python and then they are
really shown how coherent good you know
high quality code base looks like in
that language and what are the problems
that you see in that language so that's
the very technical side of it and I
think that can be very valuable to
people you can train that yourself or
the organization can take part of that
and just help the people understand how
that looks like there the social aspects
of it and there are also the process
aspects which I think are often
overlooked people have set every Terry
rules like two people have to look at
that code review otherwise it can't be
you know merged could be a good thing
but maybe it's not fitting your process
maybe it's not fitting your goals again
so I think yeah there is still a lot
that can be done
so I think most of what you're saying
again is you really need to be explicit
about your goals doing a code review
yeah exactly so one of the things that I
do in the workshop that I give they're
normally company internal workshop so
they're all people from from the same
company and we work on that together
because it's really about also that the
engineers you know have a say in what
works and what doesn't work because
otherwise they will find ways around it
so if you sad every Theory rules that
makes no sense people will game the
system and they know what they are doing
right so I think on one hand you have to
empower the people but also empower them
to address bottlenecks that you see in
the process that you might enforce on
them
so I want to talk a little bit more
about different programming languages
because programming language is very
lots in readability and how easy it is
to identify a certain feature and you
mentioned that already a little bit when
you're just said you know I have to
Google something for a certain
programming language so would you say a
code review for let's say COBOL is very
different from a code review for Haskell
or would you say it's all the same
well the code review itself I think the
pure mechanics are very very similar
right but there's a difference in the
effectiveness of code abuse and how long
it takes people to review that code and
in what you should look for right so in
C you will look for different issues
than in Java or C sharp language right
where you know that you are having for
example the the garbage collection and
that helps you and things like that
right so that's why I think it's
important to know about the specific of
your language and then look for specific
patterns that are tricky in that
language and so I would say yeah the
code abuse look different for the
different programming languages even
though from the outside it looks all the
same but we also saw is we did a study
at Microsoft where we looked at how code
to your feedback differs depending on
the kind of code you review and we saw
that example for deployment code right
Yama files and things like that they are
just really hard to review so there is
less valuable code review feedback
happening then in the normal see shop
files for example and we also saw that
some of the programming languages seem
to be more difficult than others and
people have harder times to point out
issues
well yeah but I have a follow-up
question because now I'm curious that if
people review llamó less than in our
programming language is that because of
inherent aspects of the programming
language or is it just because it's way
less likely that people will know
something now yeah more than about
c-sharp
so maybe a deeper form of that question
would be do you really need a very good
understanding of a programming language
in order to be able to give a good code
review or are there generic questions
you can always ask even if you lack a
good understanding of the programming
language or the technology
secondhand I think there are several
things that you just address that I
would like to come back so especially
with the Yammer files I think there are
several things that can influence the
outcomes right it's a study and so we
couldn't control for everything I think
for the it's a really interpretations of
the results that we think for the yama
file it could be that it's just that the
syntax highlighting isn't so nice right
or that they are just really large files
some of the things that you said that
people are not familiar with that or not
so many people are familiar definitely
placed into that because what we see and
that's there's very strong evidence for
that is that people that aren't familiar
with the technologies or the code base
event right it's not even the
technologies but the code base that they
are looking at you really have a hard
time giving valuable feedback so what we
saw for example is people that are just
starting within a team they are on
boarded in a team and even if they are
seniors they take quite probably half a
year to give the same constant valuable
feedback as their peers and that has to
do that they don't know and it's also
very advised that people that you ask
for feedback have at least reviewed the
code you know especially this piece of
code that you're looking at or changed
it and they will give much more valuable
feedback so yeah experience has a lot to
do with the way you can give valuable
feedback and you can't contribute it's
just if you don't have the experience it
will take you much longer and it will be
very hard for you to give interesting
feedback or helpful constructive
feedback
yeah that makes sense in order to give
some feedback at least you have to know
something but then another question
popped into my mind you also mentioned
with the Yammer files you said well
maybe they don't have proper syntax
highlighting in most IDs and that got me
thinking of to support in general which
was also my list of things I wanted to
ask you what type of tool supports can
really support a code review what do you
need what can really help is this within
IDE is this within a version control
system what are features that really
support code reviews well yeah it's a
broad question
so I hinted at that at the beginning so
in the basic form people are just
sending emails right so they put them
add some patches some some code files
maybe some you know divs that don't have
a lot of visual clues and they write
emails back and forth and then we can go
to dedicated solutions standalone
solutions that obviously they are really
trying to focus on how can you improve
that experience and they will have
Tiffany can you know switch up the way
you see the code maybe you have side by
side divs maybe it's you know merged in
then a lot of them allowed to
communicate per line or even you know
have multiple lines also github right
now edit the multiple line comment which
for standalone tools has been already
there but now you can also add Kitter
for example select multiple lines and
comment there and those commenting
things are nowadays very often in such a
threat you can imagine that like for
example in social social platforms like
Twitter Facebook but you have like one
person is commenting and then you can
reply and you see very nice the nesting
of it you can resolve comments there is
really a lot that happens around this
commenting functionality how can you
resolve threads how can you have pending
then there are two links around that
help you to don't forget to code reviews
right so maybe de ping you in the chat
maybe in slag or in Microsoft teams and
nowadays I see more and more tools that
allow a much more
well collaborative way of code tributes
and more integrated so there are also
tools that allow you again to stay in
your IDE and write a comment and maybe
that the person that you want to talk
about you look that up with for example
get blame and you know and you write
them a message and you can do that
within the IDE so there is quite some
development happening in that space and
I think they are getting more modern
right now and I think it's really going
towards this continuous feedback loop
this continuous and collaboration
efforts that you have yeah that's
definitely a space where a loss happens
like within IDs and within get up so
many things are changing and also taking
this into account while you were talking
I was also thinking all those means of
communication like life communication
slack email how do you make sure to
really safe their richness of data that
is generated within a code review like
if someone says on slack hey maybe you
haven't implemented this architecture
passing correctly maybe we should do
this and that then where does that
information live how does that reach the
code day is that a new person that reads
the code can also read this information
about stuff that was considered about
the code base yeah that's true so I
think that traceability is a very
important aspect as well for code abuse
so that's for example some of the teams
that I've worked with at Microsoft would
require you to somehow put it into the
code review when you had for example an
ad-hoc spontaneous over-the-shoulder
review that the outcome at least of the
code review is documented in the code
review tool I think for people that
really sort of open source community for
example that does code review via email
but there's the mailing list and with
the mailing list you have this
traceability maybe not as much as you
want because you have to search right
it's based on text search and things
like that but there is some parts of
that and I think the code review tools
nowadays more and more look for link
ability so that you can within your code
to be a tool you link to your
backtracking you link to your design
documents you link to your get commit
so yeah traceability I think it's an
important part and people are working on
it how can you make that better because
there's a lot of information so for
example if you're in your IDE should you
have should you see the comments that
happened on that line but which one
should you look at right they are not
all as relevant maybe the typos you
don't have to look at they don't give
you so much information but if there was
a design discussion maybe you should
have access to that information so I
think people are working on that and
it's getting better but they still let's
plenty to do that it can be improved
there's one last topic I want to talk
about and I know you tweet a lot about
code reviews about working remote amount
starting a company and there's one tweet
that really hit me that I read a while
ago where you said drinkie code reviews
you have to balance speed and rigor you
can have a three-hour code review where
you really catch everything or you can
have a five minute go review well maybe
some useful things are sad but
definitely no everything so how do you
balance those things how do you know
when to do - one form and when to do the
other
yeah well that's sweet I'm a super
curious person and I really love to hear
what other think so that was the
original for this tweet and I kept it
tweet on purpose I kept it quite open so
it was vague and I wanted to see how
people interpreted Street and many
people I think interpreted that as you
sad that they look at their personal
experience and how fast they actually go
over one single review right so you get
some code and how much time do you spend
on that review and finally I gave a talk
about that in a tech event recently
where it's called oh no I am the slowest
code reviewer on the team right where we
discussed and that's also what I do in
my workshops so we discuss what does it
mean to be the slowest code reviewer on
the team right but what are the
implications and should I go you know
should I spend a lot of time should I be
very specific you know should I use my
checklist and really look at each line
or you know could I just you know look
over and said oh it looks fine to me but
what I also had in mind when I tweeted
that is the overall review process
because it turns out you know how fast
you go through that review has only a a
really small impact on how fast people
get their code via feedback what's much
more important for speed and rigor is
the overall process that you design so I
would say it's important that you look
through the reviews yeah carefully
really carefully and think how can I add
value still have this question in mind
how can I add value here but also to
think about your overall process as
every code change need a review right
this does a small trivial change and fix
that I know we'll be okay do I have to
wait you know an hour that somebody has
time to look over it and says that's
okay maybe maybe not I'm not saying that
it's always one or the other but to
reflect on that the same so if you think
about speed and rigor but I really find
interesting is so there's this idea that
two reviewers is a really good number
there has been Studies on the
that see that the most value is provided
by to reviewer if you're adding more you
don't get you know as much valuable
feedback as before so there's you know
it is a curve but Google for example for
70% of their changes they have only one
person one additional person to look
over that and they are obviously missing
out on the rigor and I'm not saying the
rigor off that one person but the over a
process rigor because there is one
person less that looks rate but what
they achieve with it is that they have
an average four hours turnaround time
for code reviews which is really really
fast industry standard for advanced
companies is 18 24 hours something like
that right some people wait for weeks
for code reviews um so yeah this record
versus speed I think can be I think it's
more applicable for the overall process
than for the individual but I like to to
ask those questions because it shows
that people reflect on themselves right
do you think or how fast do I go or our
code we process is really slow we should
just spend less time you know looking at
the actual lines of code but by the
problems and the bottlenecks most of the
time lie in the process and as an
individual again it's not how fast you
go through the code it's maybe have you
set dedicated times aside do you know
when you're doing the code reviews you
know or are the code reviews piling up
and you're you have to wait several days
until you do them or the code you will
really large I mean that's one of the
things that it makes really hard if you
have to set two hours aside to go
through a code review and you've know
already it will be overwhelming but they
were progress donation set in and things
like that so this again this is a
personal process perspective today I
think have a big impact on the speed and
the rigor
question yeah that was a long answer but
is what this this tweet had very many
facets I liked it a lot because how
people answer so in essence I think what
you're saying again is it's all about
goal-setting and Google the goal might
be speed turnover speed so then they do
really quickly but then another con
the goal might be rigor and then they
might have as a result a slower turnover
time yeah true that's that's very true
yeah one more question if people want to
know more about you or the work you do
or the workshops that you give where can
I find more information so I have my
personal website it's it's my name it's
Mikaela Kyla calm where you can find
everything I write about code reviews
because I write a lot I also run a
newsletter about
engineering software engineering team
building and culture and things like
that and I'm on Twitter you can find me
on Twitter that's em and then Kyla gr e
il er and finally I have a podcast that
I would love if you would listen in it's
called software engineering unlocked
where I well interview developers
experienced developers from different
companies about their self engineering
practices that they have in their
companies fantastic we'll make sure that
all of those links are in the show notes
in addition to all the things you said
the tools you mentioned the papers you
refer to thanks a lot for being on the
show with us today Michaela yeah thank
you feeling it was really a pleasure
this is Felina for software engineering
radio thanks for listening to se radio
an educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website that will
reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us a team
at SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening